<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Architecture on Raghu Vijaykumar</title>
    <link>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/tags/architecture/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Architecture on Raghu Vijaykumar</description>
    <image>
      <title>Raghu Vijaykumar</title>
      <url>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.127.0</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 17:12:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ensuring Resiliency: High Availability and Disaster Recovery Strategies</title>
      <link>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/posts/architecture/how-to-ha-and-dr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 17:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/posts/architecture/how-to-ha-and-dr/</guid>
      <description>High Availability (HA) and Disaster Recovery (DR) are critical strategies in cloud computing to ensure services are continuously available and resilient against failures.
Designing HA &amp;amp; DR Most of the services can be differentiated as compute and storage; these are the two key components when building resilient software architectures. Here is a generic diagram for HA and DR.
HA Key Components Auto-Scaling: Adjusts the number of instances based on traffic demands.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enterprise Product - Things to consider</title>
      <link>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/posts/architecture/enterprise-product/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 17:12:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://raghu-vijaykumar.github.io/blog/posts/architecture/enterprise-product/</guid>
      <description>Developing an enterprise product is a complex endeavour that demands meticulous planning and execution. Here&amp;rsquo;s a comprehensive checklist that can serve as your roadmap to success. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re launching a web server or a multifaceted application, these steps are critical for ensuring business continuity
Business Case Business Need is defined Product architecture and high level technical architecture is determined High-level technical plan is devised Estimated Budgets allocated Migration strategy, if applicable, is established Service Delivery Procedures are determined Necessary resources assigned Definite Commitment to technical and security standards established.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
